<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
  <chapter id="userguide">
    <title>User Guide</title>

    <section id="userguide.firsttime">
      <title>Running for the first time</title>

      <para>The first time you run FreeGuide it asks you some questions and
      then asks whether you want to choose your channels. You should normally
      leave this option ticked.</para>

      <para>If you followed the installation instructions for your platform
      exactly, but you get an error here, it's a bug - sorry! - <link
      linkend="contact">contact us</link> and we'll sort you out.</para>

      <para>If all has gone well, FreeGuide will know what channels you want,
      but won't be able to show any programmes because you haven't downloaded
      them yet. It will ask you whether you want to go to the download screen.
      Connect to the Internet, and click <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>. Cross
      your fingers and wait. If all is well, the listings should eventually
      download (it can take some time), and you can click
      <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to start using FreeGuide. If you have problems
      have a look at the <link linkend="help.faq">FAQ</link>.</para>

      <note>
        <para>If you very quickly get an "<literal>Execution Error</literal>"
        message, check that you're connected to the Internet and try again. If
        you wait quite a while and then get the "<literal>Execution
        Error</literal>" message, everything may still be alright - click
        "<guibutton>Continue</guibutton>" to see.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="userguide.mainscreen">
      <title>The main screen</title>

      <para>On the main screen time advances from left to right (click
      "<guibutton>Go To Now</guibutton>" to see what's on now), and the
      channels are shown one below another.</para>

      <para>The <guibutton>+</guibutton> and <guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons
      change the day you are looking at, or you can choose a day from the
      list.</para>

      <para>You can double-click on a programme (making it change colour) to
      add it to your personalised TV guide for today, which is shown in the
      bottom section of the window. You can change the colours, but the
      default setup has green for programmes that are in your personalised
      guide, and pink for movies.</para>

      <para>Clicking "<guibutton>Print this personalised listing</guibutton>"
      will open up your web browser with your customised TV guide, and you can
      print it by choosing "<guimenu>File</guimenu>" and then
      "<guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem>" in your browser.</para>

      <para>To change the order of your channels, or only show some of them at
      a time, use the "<guimenuitem>Channel Sets</guimenuitem>" option on the
      "<guimenu>Tools</guimenu>" menu. After you've made one, you can choose a
      channel set with the dropdown list at the top-right of the main
      screen.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="userguide.features">
      <title>Features</title>

      <para>You can make programmes highlight themselves by adding them to
      your favourites list (under the "<guimenu>Tools</guimenu>" menu click
      "<guimenuitem>Favourites</guimenuitem>"). Any programme matching a
      favourite will be ticked automatically. You can always un-tick
      programmes if you wish. You can also make a programme a favourite by
      right-clicking it and choosing "<guibutton>Add to
      Favourites</guibutton>".</para>

      <para>Check out the "<guimenuitem>Options</guimenuitem>" item on the
      "<guimenu>Tools</guimenu>" menu to customise FreeGuide and alter lots of
      options.</para>
      
      <para>To search for programmes, click "<guimenuitem>Search</guimenuitem>"
      on the "<guimenu>Tools</guimenu>" menu.</para>
      
      <para>To view today's programmes in a list format, choose
      "<guimenuitem>Vertical</guimenuitem>"
      on the "<guimenu>View</guimenu>" menu.  To get back to the normal view,
      choose "<guimenuitem>Horizontal</guimenuitem>" from the same menu.</para>
      
      <para>To change the order of the channels or to see smaller groups of
      channels instead of everything at once, click the drop-down in the
      top right which says "<guimenuitem>All Channels</guimenuitem>" and choose
      "<guimenuitem>Edit channel sets...</guimenuitem>".  When you have
      created a channel set, its name will appear in this list.  Choose it
      and the set of channels you can see will change to your selection.</para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="userguide.choosing_channels">
      <title>Choosing Channels</title>

      <para>During FreeGuide's "First Time Wizard" you have a chance to choose
      which channels you want to download.  If you want to change your mind
      later, go to the <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> menu and click
      <guimenuitem>Choose Channels for XMLTV</guimenuitem>.  This allows you to
      tell FreeGuide's listings grabber for your country which channels you
      want.  Follow the instructions and answer the questions, and your
      configuration will be modified.  In order to see any changes you made
      reflected in the listings you can see, you will need to re-download
      listings, by clicking the <guibutton>Download Listings</guibutton>
      button on the main screen.</para>
      
      <para>The difference between doing <guimenuitem>Choose Channels for
      XMLTV</guimenuitem> and making a different channel set is that channel
      sets only affect what is displayed, not what is downloaded.  To change
      what is downloaded, you need to click <guimenuitem>Choose Channels for
      XMLTV</guimenuitem>.</para>
      
    </section>

    <section id="userguide.look_and_feel">
      <title>Styling FreeGuide: Look-and-Feel</title>

      <para>You can style/theme FreeGuide by using so-called <emphasis>Look
      and Feels</emphasis>.  You can change the look-and-feel used by FreeGuide
      by going to the <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> menu and choosing
      <guimenuitem>Options</guimenuitem>.  Now click on
      <guilabel>General</guilabel> and choose a look-and-feel from the
      drop-down.</para>
      
      <section id="userguide.look_and_feel.installing_new">
      
        <title>Installing new Look-and-Feels</title>
        
        <para>You can download Java Look-and-Feels from lots of places.
        Some sites, such as <ulink
        url="http://www.javootoo.com/">javootoo.com</ulink> provide
        links to many different look-and-feels that are available for
        download under licenses varying from open source to proprietary and
        commercial. You may also want to try a search on your favorite
        search engine.</para>
        
        <para>When you download a look-and-feel, it should include
        instructions for installing it. Some may have
        requirements that others do not; for example, some will require
        you to specify additional information on the command line to use
        the look-and-feel. Therefore, it is important that you read the
        instructions that came with your look-and-feel.</para>
        
        <para>In all cases, however, the look-and-feel must appear in
        FreeGuide's classpath. To include the look-and-feel in the classpath,
        modify the shortcut you are using to start FreeGuide to include
        the <parameter>-classpath</parameter> command-line option. The
        command line should look something like those shown below (make
        sure you use the correct locations for your files):</para>
        
        <programlisting>javaw -classpath "C:\path\to\my\LookAndFeel.jar" ...</programlisting>
        
        <para>Where "..." means fill in the rest of the shortcut command that
        was already present.</para>
        
      </section>
      
      <section id="userguide.look_and_feel.gtk">
      
        <title>The GTK Look-and-Feel</title>
        
        <para>The GTK look-and-feel is designed to look like the rest of your
        desktop if you are using the GNOME desktop environment on Linux.  However,
        Windows users can also use the GTK look-and-feel, if you download the
        Java JDK (developers' kit) instead of just the JRE (runtime environment). 
        The advantage of the GTK look-and-feel is that you can use any of many
        available the GNOME desktop themes with it, which opens up a large array
        of possible looks for FreeGuide.</para>
        
        <para>GTK+ themes are available from a number of websites,
        including <ulink
        url="http://art.gnome.org/themes/gtk2/">GNOME</ulink> and <ulink
        url="http://themes.freshmeat.net/">freshmeat.net</ulink>.</para>
      
      </section>
     
    </section>
  </chapter>

