<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
  <chapter id="userguide">
    <title>User Guide</title>

    <section id="userguide.firsttime">
      <title>Running for the first time</title>

      <para>The first time you run FreeGuide it asks you some questions and
      then offers to configure your grabber. You should normally leave this
      option ticked.</para>

      <para>If you followed the installation instructions for your platform
      exactly, but you get an error here, it's a bug - sorry! - <link
      linkend="contact">contact us</link> and we'll sort you out.</para>

      <para>If all has gone well, FreeGuide will know what channels you want,
      but won't be able to show any programmes because you haven't downloaded
      them yet. It will ask you whether you want to go to the download screen.
      Connect to the Internet, and click <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>. Cross
      your fingers and wait. If all is well, the listings should eventually
      download (it can take some time), and you can click
      <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to start using FreeGuide. If you have problems
      have a look at the <link linkend="help.faq">FAQ</link>.</para>

      <note>
        <para>If you very quickly get an "<literal>Execution Error</literal>"
        message, check that you're connected to the Internet and try again. If
        you wait quite a while and then get the "<literal>Execution
        Error</literal>" message, everything may still be alright - click
        "<guibutton>Continue</guibutton>" to see.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="userguide.mainscreen">
      <title>The main screen</title>

      <para>On the main screen time advances from left to right (click
      "<guibutton>Go To Now</guibutton>" to see what's on now), and the
      channels are shown one below another.</para>

      <para>The <guibutton>+</guibutton> and <guibutton>-</guibutton> buttons
      change the day you are looking at, or you can choose a day from the
      list.</para>

      <para>You can double-click on a programme (making it change colour) to
      add it to your personalised TV guide for today, which is shown in the
      bottom section of the window. You can change the colours, but the
      default setup has green for programmes that are in your personalised
      guide, and pink for movies.</para>

      <para>Clicking "<guibutton>Print this personalised listing</guibutton>"
      will open up your web browser with your customised TV guide, and you can
      print it by choosing "<guimenu>File</guimenu>" and then
      "<guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem>" in your browser.</para>

      <para>To change the order of your channels, or only show some of them at
      a time, use the "<guimenuitem>Channel Sets</guimenuitem>" option on the
      "<guimenu>Tools</guimenu>" menu. After you've made one, you can choose a
      channel set with the dropdown list at the top-right of the main
      screen.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="userguide.features">
      <title>Features</title>

      <para>You can make programmes highlight themselves by adding them to
      your favourites list (under the "<guimenu>Tools</guimenu>" menu click
      "<guimenuitem>Favourites</guimenuitem>"). Any programme matching a
      favourite will be ticked automatically. You can always un-tick
      programmes if you wish. You can also make a programme a favourite by
      right-clicking it and choosing "<guibutton>Add to
      Favourites</guibutton>".</para>

      <para>Check out the "<guimenuitem>Options</guimenuitem>" item on the
      "<guimenu>Tools</guimenu>" menu to customise FreeGuide and alter lots of
      options.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="userguide.look_and_feel">
      <title>Styling FreeGuide: Look and Feel</title>

      <para>You can style/theme FreeGuide by using so-called <emphasis>Look
      and Feels</emphasis>. This page tries to give you some answers to the
      questions you might have.</para>

      <qandaset>
        <qandadiv>
          <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.skins">
            <question>
              <para>Does FreeGuide support skins/themes?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para><productname>FreeGuide</productname> (starting with
              version <productnumber>0.7</productnumber>) supports
              <productname>Java</productname>'s Pluggable Look and Feel
              (L&amp;F). Most of the available L&amp;F's provide a single
              "look," but some, such as the GTK+ and Synth Looks and Feels,
              provide support for themes (skins).</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

	  <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.whatislaf">
            <question>
              <para>What are Looks and Feels?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>Looks and Feels (L&amp;F's) are a means by which a
              programmer or an end-user can change the appearance of a Java
              application without rewriting or recompiling the
              application.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

	  <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.setlaf">
            <question>
              <para>How do I set the L&amp;F used by FreeGuide?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>Select
              <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>|<guimenuitem>Options</guimenuitem> from
              the FreeGuide menu. The options for <guilabel>Layout</guilabel>
              include a combo box (drop down list) that lists all of the
              L&amp;F's available on your system. Select the L&amp;F you want
              to use and click the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button.</para>

              <para>If you have installed a L&amp;F that FreeGuide was unable
              to identify, you may type its class name into the combo box.
              Note that you must provide the fully-qualified classname - one
              that includes several words separated by periods, such as
              <filename>javax.swing.plaf.metal.MetalLookAndFeel</filename>.
              The fully qualified classname should be given in the L&amp;F's
              documentation.</para>

              <para>If you type in the class name and nothing happens,
              FreeGuide is unable to find the specified class. Make sure you
              spelled the class name correctly. If everything is spelled
              correctly, make sure you installed the L&amp;F correctly.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

	  <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.installlaf">
            <question>
              <para>How do I install new L&amp;F's.</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>When you download a L&amp;F, it should include
              instructions for installing the L&amp;F. Some may have
              requirements that others do not; for example, some will require
              you to specify additional information on the command line to use
              the L&amp;F. Therefore, it is important that you read the
              instructions that came with your L&amp;F.</para>

              <para>In all cases, however, the L&amp;F must appear in
              FreeGuide's classpath. To include the L&amp;F in the classpath,
              modify the shortcut you are using to start FreeGuide to include
              the <parameter>-classpath</parameter> command-line option. The
              command line should look something like those shown below (make
              sure you use the correct locations for your files):</para>

              <para>For Windows</para>

              <programlisting>javaw -classpath "C:\path\to\my\LookAndFeel.jar" -jar "C:\Program Files\FreeGuide\FreeGuide.jar"</programlisting>

              <para>Or, for Unix-like operating systems:</para>

              <programlisting>java -classpath "/path/to/my/LookAndFeel.jar" -jar "/usr/share/freeguide/FreeGuide.jar"</programlisting>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

	  <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.gtklaf">
            <question>
              <para>What about the GTK+ L&amp;F?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>The GTK+ L&amp;F was designed to provide the look and feel
              of a native application developed with the <ulink
              url="http://www.gtk.org/">GTK+</ulink> toolkit (as are many
              applications for Unix-like operating systems - such as GNU/Linux
              - and even some applications that run on Windows). Since the
              GTK+ toolkit provides support for themes (which are functionally
              equivalent to skins), the GTK+ L&amp;F provides theme/skin
              support.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

	  <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.gtkforgtk">
            <question>
              <para>Do I need to install GTK+ to use the GTK+ L&amp;F?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>No. The GTK+ L&amp;F performs the work normally
              accomplished by GTK+ theme engines to allow its use on any
              system - regardless of whether the system uses (or even
              supports) GTK+. Therefore, as long as you have the GTK+ L&amp;F
              available, you can use the GTK+ L&amp;F. Note that you will also
              need to make GTK+ themes available to use different GTK+
              themes.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

	  <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.gtknotlisted">
            <question>
              <para>The GTK+ L&amp;F sounds great, but it's not listed as
              available. Why not?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>The GTK+ L&amp;F is a brand-new addition to Java. It is
              only included in Java 2 version 1.4.2 and above. Make sure you
              have the right version of Java. You can determine your Java
              version by executing the following command from the Command
              Prompt or shell:</para>

              <programlisting>java -version</programlisting>

              <para>If you're using Microsoft Windows, please see the next
              question.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

	  <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.nogtk142">
            <question>
              <para>I have Java 2 version 1.4.2 or above and I still don't see
              GTK+. What's wrong?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>Sun decided not to include the GTK+ L&amp;F with the Java
              2 Runtime Environment (JRE) for Windows. Currently, the only
              available option is to install the <ulink
              url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/download.html">Java 2
              Software Development Kit (SDK)</ulink> for Windows. NOTE: You do
              not need the J2EE with J2SE package or the NetBeans IDE with
              J2SE COBUNDLE. You want J2SE SDK.</para>

              <para>If you're not using Windows, you may be using an
              implementation of Java that was created by a vendor other than
              Sun Microsystems. If that's the case, you will need to <ulink
              url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/download.html">download</ulink>
              Sun's implementation of Java to get the GTK+ theme. If Sun
              doesn't provide a version for your platform, you're out of
              (legal) options.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

	  <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.morethemes">
            <question>
              <para>Where can I get more GTK+ themes?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>GTK+ themes are available from a number of websites,
              including <ulink
              url="http://art.gnome.org/themes/gtk2/">GNOME</ulink> and <ulink
              url="http://themes.freshmeat.net/">freshmeat.net</ulink>;
              however, make sure you download supported themes.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

	  <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.gtknotright">
            <question>
              <para>My GTK+ theme doesn't look right (or doesn't work). What's
              wrong?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>Currently, the GTK+ L&amp;F only supports a subset of the
              themes available for GTK+. Themes must be GTK+ 2 themes and may
              only use the Default, pixmap, and/or bluecurve theme engines.
              What does all that mean? If you really want to know, I suggest
              you go to the <ulink url="http://www.gtk.org/">GTK+
              websit</ulink>e and start reading. After all, this is a
              FreeGuide FAQ. :)</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

          <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.gtkthemesupported">
            <question>
              <para>So, how do I know if a GTK+ theme is supported?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>In truth, the best way to find out is to try the theme.
              Even if the theme is not fully supported, you might like the
              results; and since it is a "Look and Feel," if you like the look
              and you like the feel, it works for you!</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

          <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.changetheme">
            <question>
              <para>You said the GTK+ L&amp;F supports themes. How do I change
              my theme?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>First, you'll need some themes. Once you've downloaded one
              or more themes to try, install the theme (as described in the
              next two paragraphs).</para>

              <para>If you're using a Unix-like operating system, use the tool
              provided by your distribution vendor to install and select the
              theme. Now, simply start FreeGuide and, if you haven't already
              done so, select the GTK+ L&amp;F and enjoy the new look. In
              general, themes are installed by extracting their files into the
              <filename>${USER}/.themes</filename> directory. If you do not
              have a tool for working with GTK+ themes, <ulink
              url="http://www.muhri.net/nav.php3?node=gts">GTK Theme Switch
              2</ulink> is a nice lightweight program for installing and
              selecting themes. Note: If you do not want to install and/or
              select the theme, you may follow the Windows instructions
              below.</para>

              <para>If you're using Windows (or you don't want to install the
              theme on your Unix-like operating system), it's not necessary to
              install the theme. Extract the theme files to a directory,
              keeping each theme in its own directory, and keep all the theme
              directories together in a single directory to make them easy to
              find (I recommend using <filename>C:\gtk</filename> since it's
              short and easy to type).</para>

              <para>Since most of the themes will be distributed in "tarballs"
              (a common way to distribute software for Unix-like operating
              systems), you will need an extraction tool that can handle tape
              archive files (tar files) and GZIP and/or BZIP2 compression. One
              such tool for Windows is <ulink
              url="http://www.7-zip.org/">7-Zip</ulink>.</para>

              <para>Once you've extracted the themes, you're ready to use
              them. To do so, just specify the location of the
              <filename>gtkrc</filename> file in the
              <filename>swing.gtkthemefile</filename> system property on the
              command line, as shown below:</para>

              <para>For Windows</para>

              <programlisting>javaw -Dswing.gtkthemefile="C:\gtk\Theme Name\gtk-2.0\gtkrc" -jar "C:\Program Files\FreeGuide\FreeGuide.jar"</programlisting>

              <para>Or, for Unix-like operating systems:</para>

              <programlisting>java -Dswing.gtkthemefile="${HOME}/.themes/Theme Name/gtk-2.0/gtkrc" -jar "/usr/share/freeguide/FreeGuide.jar"</programlisting>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

          <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.gtkchanged">
            <question>
              <para>Why doesn't FreeGuide notice when I change my System GTK+
              theme?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>The GTK+ L&amp;F is not actually using the GTK+ theme
              engine to draw components of FreeGuide. Instead, it performs the
              work normally done by the theme engine itself, but does not
              detect changes to the system-define theme. Therefore, to get
              FreeGuide to notice the change to your theme, simply restart
              FreeGuide. Note that future versions of the GTK+ L&amp;F may
              support detection of changes to the system theme, but until then
              restarting FreeGuide is the only way to change themes.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

          <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.slow">
            <question>
              <para>Since I changed my L&amp;F, FreeGuide seems slow.
              Why?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>Well, you can't get something for nothing--with the
              exception of good quality open source software, of course! Some
              L&amp;F's are slower than others, some L&amp;F's claim to be
              faster than the default Java L&amp;F (Metal), so you might want
              to try experimenting with other L&amp;F's. If you've got your
              heart set on the L&amp;F you're using, you'll have to get used
              to its performance.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

          <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.longerstartup">
            <question>
              <para>Since I changed my L&amp;F, FreeGuide seems to take 4.5ms
              longer to start up. Why?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>The Java installation on your system specifies a default
              L&amp;F to use when none is specifically requested. Therefore,
              when you start FreeGuide, Java uses its default L&amp;F until
              FreeGuide changes the L&amp;F to the one you specified in your
              preferences. If you tell Java to use your preferred L&amp;F,
              FreeGuide won't need to change the L&amp;F after startup.</para>

              <para>To specify the L&amp;F, you may either change your
              installation's default L&amp;F (which will affect
              <emphasis>all</emphasis> Java programs you use) or specify the
              default L&amp;F on the command line. To change your
              installation's default, edit the file
              <filename>%JAVA_HOME%/lib/swing.properties</filename> (you may
              have to create the file) and add the line (or edit the one
              starting with <varname>swing.defaultlaf</varname> to look like
              the following):</para>

              <programlisting>swing.defaultlaf=javax.swing.plaf.metal.MetalLookAndFeel</programlisting>

              <para>To change the default L&amp;F for FreeGuide only, specify
              the L&amp;F classname as the value for the
              <varname>swing.defaultlaf</varname> system property on the
              command line. The command line should look something like those
              shown below (make sure you use the correct locations for your
              files):</para>

              <para>For Windows</para>

              <programlisting>javaw -classpath "C:\path\to\my\LookAndFeel.jar" -Dswing.defaultlaf="javax.swing.plaf.metal.MetalLookAndFeel" -jar "C:\Program Files\FreeGuide\FreeGuide.jar"</programlisting>

              <para>Or, for Unix-like operating systems:</para>

              <programlisting>java -classpath "/path/to/my/LookAndFeel.jar" -Dswing.defaultlaf="javax.swing.plaf.metal.MetalLookAndFeel" -jar "/ur/share/freeguide/FreeGuide.jar"</programlisting>

              <para>Note that the Metal L&amp;F is most likely the default on
              your Java installation, so the above command lines and
              properties file would do nothing. Instead, use the fully
              qualified classname of the L&amp;F you want to use. The fully
              qualified classname should be given in the L&amp;F's
              documentation.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

          <qandaentry id="userguide.look_and_feel.wheretofindmore">
            <question>
              <para>Where can I find more L&amp;F's?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>Some sites, such as <ulink
              url="http://www.javootoo.com/">javootoo.com</ulink> provide
              links to many different L&amp;F's that are available for
              download under licenses varying from open source to proprietary
              commercial. You may also want to try a search on your favorite
              search engine, for example on <ulink
              url="http://www.google.com/search?q=%2B%22Java%22+%2B%22Look+and+Feel%22+%2B%22download%22&amp;start=0&amp;ie=utf-8&amp;oe=utf-8">Google</ulink>.</para>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>
        </qandadiv>
      </qandaset>
    </section>
  </chapter>